Hey everyone, it's Richard. You're
watching the Plain Bagel. It's 2026 and
we are back to being a tariff channel. I
know you've all been craving that tariff
content and more tariff updates. And boy
oh boy, has has the new year been
delivering. Uh so far already in January
we've seen Trump impose new tariffs on
semiconductors, threaten European
countries with tariffs for not letting
him take over Greenland, the European
Union lawmakers suspending their US
trade deal agreed to last year amid the
Greenland [music] threats. And Trump
suddenly walking back everything after
reaching a supposed framework deal with
NATO around Iceland
or Greenland, the the icy one. But
that's not what we're talking about
today. Maybe it should be given how
unhinged it all is. Uh but today we're
talking about a different area of tariff
news that's for me anyway closer to
home. Uh because on January 14th,
Canadian Prime Minister Mark Carney
landed in China to further trade talks
with the country. The first Prime
Minister to visit the nation since 2017.
And in addition to warming what's
previously been a pretty hostile
relationship between the two countries,
we saw the trade talks end with a trade
deal between Canada and China that among
other things will see Canada wave its
100% tariff for up to 49,000 China
produced electric vehicles which is
pretty meaningful. Canada will now be
the only member of the KUSMA agreement
or USMCA agreement in the United States
that will allow Chinese vehicles into
their country without charging
exorbitant levies. And it's been viewed
by some as a direct rebuff of the United
States. After all, the US largely views
China as a key global adversary, and
Canada has historically been heavily
dependent on the United States for
trade, with the country sending over 3/4
of its exports to the United States in
2024. So cozying up to China is a pretty
bold move, one that many feared might
lead to retaliation from a president
who's tariffed Islands of Penguins for
less. So what did Trump have to say
about the deal?
>> That's okay. That's what he should be
doing. I mean, it's a good thing for him
to sign a trade deal. If you can get a
deal with China, you should do that.
>> Nonetheless, even with Trump seemingly
being chill about the deal, it still
proved somewhat controversial among
other US officials and even here within
Canada. Uh, with some lamenting that
this will hurt Canada's attempt to
normalize relations with the United
States and comments from Carney about a
quote new world order, stoking fears
that the country is sliding under
China's growing influence. But what
terms did Canada actually agree to here
and what does it mean for the country's
economy and its relationship with China
and the United States? Well, that's what
I want to cover in today's video to give
some context around what was actually in
this trade deal we saw announced this
past weekend. A quick thank you to
Brilliant for sponsoring today's video.
You can stick around to the end for an
exclusive deal on their platform. And
I'll include chapters in the description
if you want to skip ahead to the
different sections, including if you
just want to get to the new trade deal
uh details. But it's worth giving some
context around the Canada China
relationship especially because while
yes the thawing of relations between the
two countries is meaningful and might
lead to further integration of their two
economies and we will touch on what the
important developments from all this
really are the deal itself and
specifically around Chinese electric
vehicles uh isn't really as substantial
as people are making it out to be
online. Uh, in fact, the agreement
actually just brings Chinese electric
vehicle imports back to the level they
were just a few years ago. You see,
unbeknownst to some, Canada and China
have actually been in a bit of a trade
war for these past couple of years. It
was obviously hard to focus on given
everything else happening at the time,
but back in August of 2024, the Canadian
government in step with the United
States and the European Union announced
a 100% tariff against Chinese electric
and hybrid vehicles. Previously, the
vehicles had only faced the most favored
nation tariff of 6.1%. But citing
concerns over subsidized state directed
production and a lack of rigorous labor
and environmental standards. Canada
sought to limit imports of vehicles it
viewed as having an unfair advantage to
Canadian automakers. But the government
also highlighting the privacy and data
risk posed by Chinese vehicles given the
lack of transparency on data ownership.
At the same time, Canada imposed a 25%
tariff on steel and aluminum imports
from China, arguing that the country
threatened to flood metal markets with
China having greatly expanded its steel
making capacity under state direction
despite globally softening demand. And
there's certainly merit to concerns that
China could flood these markets. China
actually produces 2/3 of the world's
electric vehicles and over half of the
world's steel and aluminum as of 2024.
And for Canada, these categories
represented several billion dollars of
imports that the country was buying from
China. Uh in 2023, for example, Canada
actually imported 44,000 electric
vehicles from the country before the
tariff hikes caused purchases to
plummet. Now, these tariffs from Canada
were followed by retaliatory measures
from China in March of 2025 when amid
Trump's own tariff campaign against both
of these countries, we saw China itself
announced a 100% tariff on Canadian rape
seed oil, oil cakes, and peas, and a 25%
tariff on pork and seafood, with China
later adding a 75.8% tariff on Canadian
canola seed in August. Now, these
categories might sound a little random
for a country that's predominantly known
for its exports of crude oil and hockey
players, but rape seed oil is actually
Canada's largest agricultural export and
its second largest export category to
China behind only crude oil,
specifically canola oil, which is a
Canadian invention that actually stands
for Canada oil low acid. Uh, with the
canola plant being bred specifically to
reduce uric acid, which is linked to
heart problems, to make the oil
healthier for consumption.
A little Canada heritage minute there
for you. But all to say, these are
actually fairly important export
categories for Canada, especially for
the country's agricultural provinces
located in the prairies. Canola is
Canada's second largest crop behind only
wheat, and the country is the largest
producer globally of rape seed oil,
making up about a fifth of total
production. Meanwhile, China is a big
buyer of Canada's canola products,
importing over a third of the country's
total canola exports. And the other
impacted industries were notable as
well. China collectively imported
billions of dollars worth of peas, pork,
and seafood from Canada in 2024 and
takes up anywhere from a fifth to a
third of each category's total exports.
So, while trade between the two
countries includes many other categories
that fell outside the scope of this
trade war, you can still see that some
key industries were being targeted here,
and they did have a meaningful impact.
As mentioned, EV tariffs led Chinese car
imports to plummet in Canada, while
canola seed exports to China dropped
from 67.7%
of total exports through 2024 to 0% by
September 2025 with additional tariffs
brought by China in August. It all
naturally happened at a pretty bad time
with Trump's own tariffs likewise
rocking important Canadian sectors. But
as mentioned this past week, the tone of
the relationship has meaningfully
changed with the announcement of a new
Canada China trade deal after talks in
Beijing. So what's actually included in
this deal? Well, as mentioned, the
Canadian government has agreed to import
up to 49,000 Chinese electric vehicles,
representing about 3% of total new cars
sold in Canada at a reduced tariff rate
of 6.1%. reflecting the import and
tariff levels seen in Canada before the
restrictive tariffs were slapped on
China in 2024. Though, it's worth noting
that most Chinese EV imports weren't
actually for Chinese brands, but rather
for companies like Tesla and Volvo with
Chinese operations. MR Carney has
commented that this import cap could
rise 43% to as high as 70,000 vehicles
in the next 5 years. Now, in exchange
for this market access, China will be
reducing its tariff on canola oil from a
combined rate across canola categories
of 84% to 15% by March and removing
tariffs on canola meal, lobsters, crab,
and peas as of the same month with
tariff exemptions lasting until at least
the end of the year. Now, for now, it
does appear that tariffs will remain in
place on pork, albeit there is this
expectation that those will also be
lifted and the measures are expected to
add nearly $3 billion in export orders
for Canada. So you can see that when you
take the terms of the trade deal at face
value, uh we're really just seeing the
thawing of the previously icy
relationship between the two countries
and the reversal of tariffs that have
only been in place for a couple of
years. In fact, we're still seeing more
tariffs than we had prior to 2023.
Chinese steel and aluminum will still
have their full 25% tariff. And while it
now faces a reduced rate, canola seed,
Canada's largest canola export, still
faces a higher double-digit tariff here.
And while these trade categories are
important to some of Canada's provinces,
the country doesn't actually have that
sizable of a trade relationship with
China. Yes, technically China is
Canada's second largest trade partner,
and we do see 12% of imports into Canada
coming from China, but the country only
represents about 4% of Canada's own
exports. So when you consider that the
concrete aspects of this trade deal are
really just reversing again those
recently implemented tariffs, the deal
at face value doesn't represent this
seismic shift in Canada's trade
relations. What it does mean, however,
is Canada has taken its first step
towards further deepening its trade
relationship with China, which is
notable and which Canada has expressed
interest in doing with the two countries
coming to a number of softer agreements
during their talks. Uh, for example, not
long after the trade deal announcement,
we got news that beef exports from
Canada to China had restarted after
being shut out in 2021. We saw the
countries revived their joint economic
and trade commission, which has been
dormant for the past 8 years. The two
broadly committed to expanding bilateral
trade, strengthening two-way investment
and deepening cooperation. And a
statement by the prime minister's office
highlighted the expectation that within
3 years, the agreement would drive quote
considerable new Chinese joint venture
investment in Canada. And by 2030,
Canada would target to bolster exports
to China by 50%. Something that would
bring exports to the country to around
30 billion dollars annually. The
countries also agreed to increase
collaboration in a number of other
areas. And we even saw China agree to
allow visafree access for Canadians
traveling to China, which is notable
given that 9% of Canada's recent
immigrant population comes from the
country. Now, China was not the only
country Mark Carney was trying to woo
this past week. Uh we also saw the prime
minister in this international tour of
his try to drum up foreign investment in
Qar and later at the World Economic
Forum in Davos, Switzerland. And we did
see a soft agreement with Qar to invest
in infrastructure projects in Canada.
But the trade relations with China was
by far the biggest update from the trip
from a trade standpoint. As for why
Carne is specifically targeting China
here, there are a few key reasons. For
one, Canada is of course very dependent
on the United States. But with this past
year of tariffs and discussions of
making Canada the 51st state via
economic coercion, uh something that's
been an heightened issue amid all the
Greenland stuff, uh Prime Minister Mark
Carney has made diversifying trade a key
objective for the country with Mark
Carney aiming to double non- US exports
currently at 23% over the next decade,
which would bring it on par with US
exports. And China is really one of the
only countries that can compete with the
US in terms of its export purchasing
power. In 2024, the US was by far the
largest importer of products
internationally with $4.1 trillion of
imports. China was second at $3.3
trillion while Germany was third at $1.8
trillion. So while technically if you
included the EU as one entity, uh they
would be the largest market and Canada
naturally would want to broaden its
exports across more markets rather than
just shifting its dependency. China is
really the only individual country that
can compete with America's demand. This
is especially true for crude oil, which
is Canada's largest export category and
where it's particularly dependent on US
demand with 96% of crude exports going
to the US. And China is again one of the
only feasible individual players that
could substitute this demand. In fact,
internationally, China is the largest
buyer of crude oil, taking up about a
quarter of total exports and importing
almost double what we see in the US. And
luckily for Canada, there is
infrastructure to send oil to its west
coast. While most pipelines are geared
towards sending its oil south across the
border, we have recently seen the
country expand its pipeline
infrastructure to the west and agree to
build further pipelines sending oil to
the west coast where China sits as a
ready buyer. And this new infrastructure
is already seeing activity ramp up with
Chinese imports of Canadian crude likely
to have doubled in 2025 and said to move
higher still in the new year, especially
in the face of the US likely cutting the
country off of Venezuelan exports. And
finally, this trade deal with China
presents the opportunity to attract
investment dollars that the country
desperately needs. You see, the country
has long been struggling with a
productivity issue with labor
productivity plateauing while unit labor
costs have continued to climb. And the
country has seen a number of key
electric vehicle and battery projects
delayed, scrapped, or changed over the
past couple of years. So, a big push for
Mark Carney has been to revitalize the
country as a hub for infrastructure
investment with him pushing to expediate
project approvals in Canada for
so-called nation building projects in an
attempt to cut the red tape that's long
plagued construction in the country. So,
while China's not the only country
Canada's trying to attract investment
dollars from, a trade deal does make
that sort of activity more likely. But
there's certainly being the hope here
that we see Chinese EV factories built
inside Canada, which barring any
autobased retaliation, could certainly
bolster the sector after a pretty rough
couple years. Now, as you can imagine,
the decision to deepen ties with China
has not been without its controversy. Uh
while the premers of Saskatchewan and
Manitoba, both agricultural hubs,
largely applauded the trade
announcement, Doug Ford, the premier of
Ontario, Canada's auto manufacturer hub,
warned about the Chinese subsidized spy
cars that would flood Canadian markets
with many lamenting cozying up to a
country that's viewed by many as a key
national security threat, including Mark
Carney himself. I
>> think the biggest security threat to ch
Canada is China.
>> China, you say? Yeah.
>> And there's reason for these concerns.
China is of course run by an
authoritarian government and has a
history of suppression and running
state-backed cyber attacks with China
being the top source of cyber espionage,
intellectual property theft and bulk
data collection. The country has also
greatly increased its international
influence over the years in part due to
its status as the single largest global
lender, which some worry gives the
country tremendous power over nations in
debt to it. There also concerns that
this will make it harder to normalize
relationships with the United States. Uh
while Trump has threatened to throw away
the KUSMA agreement, uh the trade
agreement between the US, Mexico, and
Canada, the agreement has still allowed
Canada to have tariff-free access to the
US market for 85% of its exports,
according to the government's own 2025
budget. So, it still remains vital to
Canada's exports, and a premature
termination of the agreement would
devastate Canada's economy. In fact, the
US is actually a larger buyer of
Canada's canola products than China. And
with the KOSMA agreement up for review
in 2026, it opens the door for the US to
push for changes. And all of these are
valid concerns. Uh but it is worth
noting that China has long been a
significant trade partner for many other
developed nations in spite of all these
issues that some are now lamenting about
online. Uh the UK, Germany, and Israel,
for example, are already top importers
of Chinese electric vehicles. And the US
actually currently has a more
significant trade relationship with
China than Canada does. And of course,
Walmart appears to be changing his
position here. That of course is because
of the relationship change we've already
seen between the US and Canada. The
truth is Trump has undermined a lot of
faith that Canada had in trade with
country given the misinformation and
bogus claims that were spread as
justifications for tariffs on the
country. So, while we've seen, for
example, Howard Lutnik warned that the
China trade deal opens the door for
changing KUSMA, there's not a whole lot
of confidence that the US intends to
engage Canada in good faith anyway. And
with threats or jokes to make Canada the
51st state by economic coercion and a
push to actually annex the country of
Greenland from Denmark, it can both be
true that China is a national security
threat and that America's volatile
foreign policy itself has become a
threat that makes engaging with China
for economic diversification worth it.
Now, Canada has made it clear that
they're open to expanding trade with
many other nations as well, including
the entirety of the European Union. And
as mentioned again, when you take the
trade deal as is, it doesn't again
really represent that significant of a
change. Uh but it is likely that we
continue to see the countries try to
deepen their trade relation amid the
fallout with the United States. And if
the US continues to follow this
protectionist and isolationist approach,
we could very well see more of that from
other countries in the future. Now, I
always find with stories like this that
framing in context are really important.
It's great to highlight a headline and
figure like how many cars Canada will
now be importing from China, but putting
it in context really changes how it
might be interpreted. And if you're
interested in learning or brushing up on
data analysis or other fields like math
and programming, then you should check
out today's sponsor, Brilliant.
Brilliant offers a learning platform for
topics ranging from data to programming
and AI using interactive exercises to
let you play with the concepts that
you're learning about, which is really
what makes the offering unique. You see,
Brilliant focuses on active learning, a
method that research has shown to be
more effective than just listening to
lectures or watching videos online, and
the platform personalizes practice sets
and reviews to your level of
understanding, helping you achieve
learning goals and taking your
understanding of these concepts to the
next level. I always like to showcase
their exploring data visually course
because of how important and powerful
graphics can be at communicating data
quickly compared to just showing numbers
on a spreadsheet. And this course is
really where Brilliant shines, letting
you manipulate data sets and showing
their impacts on figures and graphs. So
to learn more about Brilliant, you can
scan the QR code on screen or visit
brilliant.org/theplain
bagel. Viewers will also get 20% off an
annual premium subscription for
unlimited daily access to everything on
Brilliant. So thank you Brilliant, and
thank you guys for joining me today. I
hope you found this video helpful. If
you did, please do make sure to like,
subscribe, all that good stuff. It does
help the channel tremendously. And let
me know your thoughts on the whole
Canada China trade deal that we saw come
out last week. Any and all thoughts
welcome in the comments down below.